Grex Staff Notes: Authentication on Grex

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Authentication on Grex is handled using the standard tools that come with the OpenBSD operating system. In particular, we use the OpenBSD bcrypt(3) hashing algorithm, and the standard 4.4BSD /etc/master.passwd database and its Berkeley DB counterparts, all managed using the tools that come with the base operating system.

In the past, however, authentication on Grex was very complex. Grex used a proprietary algorithm and format for its hashed passwords and used a heavily modified version of the software that maintains the Unix /etc/passwd file under SunOS. Special tools had to be used to work on the password database, which was very inconvenient. See the old staff notes for more information,

When Grex moved to OpenBSD from SunOS, it was decided that it was too much effort to maintain support for the custom hashing algorithm that had been used for passwords on Grex. So, the system was migrated to use the standard OpenBSD algorithm and tools instead.

Migrating from the old system to the new system was remarkably easy, but time consuming. Since passwords are hashed in a format that is difficult to invert, we could not simply "decrypt" them and rehash them using bcrypt(3). Further, we knew that asking every user on Grex to change his or her password simply would not work.

So, we came up with a different plan. The program that creates new accounts on Grex was modified to use the OpenBSD algorithm, and then the passwd(1) program was updated to always use bcrypt when a user changed his or her their password. Finally, the program that authenticates a user's password was modified so that, if it detected that a password was hashed with the old format, it would rehash the password (which it had access to) in the new format and update the database accordingly.

The bulk of users had been migrated to the OpenBSD algorithm over the course of about six months; picking up the rest of the stragglers took about a year. Grex is now free of the proprietary algorithm, account maintenance is much easier, and upgrades are simpler.

$Id: authentication.xhtml 1547 2016-09-25 14:57:21Z kentn $

Grex's Hardware and Software

Home
About Us
Get a Free Account
FAQ
Become a Member
Contact Us

Hardware

Previously, Grex was spread across several computers and other devices including the "main" Grex server, a satellite server called "gryps" that handled ancillary duties, a terminal server and a bank of modems and other associated devices. This was necessary for performance reasons at one time, as Grex was slow and underpowered and it was critical for system stability to offload as much as possible from the primary machine. But things are quite different now. Grex is far more powerful than before, and the current configuration reflects that. Furthermore, Grex spent most of its early life in space controlled by the Grex staff. It is now in a colocation facility, gryps is gone, and there is neither need nor space for a terminal server.

Main Computer and Hosting

Grex currently runs on an HP multicore system that was donated in early 2012 and replaced a system that had been purchased in 2003. The HP computer is temporary, and will be upgraded soon.

Grex is hosted at A2 Hosting, a developer friendly hosting provider in Michigan, in the mid-Western part of the United States.

Grex no longer offers dial-up service.

Software

Grex runs the OpenBSD operating system, mostly unmodified from the basic distribution. Additionally, we have installed a number of third party packages from the OpenBSD ports collection, and we also run some software either written by or closely associated with the Grex community, such as the backtalk conferencing software, the party multi-user chat program and the Orville write replacement for the standard Unix write(1) program.

At the time of this writing, all software running on Grex is Open Source. The venerable Picospan conferencing software, long a staple of life on Grex and the last non-open software we ran, has been replaced by Fronttalk. This is in sharp contrast to Grex's origins on Sun computers, where we did not even have access to the operating system source code, and changes to the system often required binary modifications!

Major Software Component Evolutions

Over Grex's history, particularly on the Sun-based computers it was started on and ran on for much of its life, the Grex staff was forced to make major changes to the operating system and related software for reasons from stability to security and performance. Lacking source code, these modifications were often via binary changes or clever use of system facilities. This has changed with the move to OpenBSD, but below are a few notes on major historical changes that were made and the current status of the analogous components. More information on the historical Grex implementations can be found here.

Internet Blocks

Soon after Grex was connected to the Internet, it was discovered that allowing anyone to access the network without any sort of authentication led to attacks against other systems being mounted from Grex; something no one had ever intended. A scheme was devised to block network access to non-validated users for all but a few well-defined services, and this was implemented by modifying the SunOS kernel to check whether a user was a member of a certain Unix group before passing on network traffic from that user. The implementation involved making changes to the symbol tables in the SunOS kernel object files to call routines written by members of the Grex staff that checked a user's credentials before passing a packet down the network stack; more details can be found here.

Furthermore, access to step past the filters was only granted to users who had chosen to become members of Grex and were active members at the time. If a user became a member, but later let her membership lapse, she would also lose access to the network.

This served Grex well for several years, but today, we implement this using the excellent OpenBSD PF packet filtering package. However, the principle remains largely the same, with minor technical differences. Furthermore, the idea of a user being a member as a prerequisite for Internet access has been removed. Users are now validated via one of several ways and remain so for as long as they have an active account. If a member lets his or her membership lapse, they do not lose their network access.

The Fork-bomb killer

Grex has always had its share of users who want to test the doors on the system's security, and some are more annoying than others. Particularly bothersome are those who run fork bombs on the system: a fork bomb is a program that executes as many copies of itself as it can, and that is all that it does. Traditionally, these slow down the system considerably.

On the Sun, Grex used the operating system's basic resource limit facility to put a cap on the total number of processes that a given user could run and this helped mitigate the problem, but did not eliminate it: even a small fork bomb could incapacitate the system. This was exacerbated by the fact that, under SunOS, one could not kill processes that were in the process of forking, making it difficult to stop this sort of attack. So, members of the Grex staff wrote software that was loaded into the kernel to detect fork bombs and kill all processes associated with the offending user, effectively ending the problem.

Two things were notable about this software, one related to implementation and the other an oversight that, to our knowledge, never led to an exploited attack. The latter deals with the fact that, under SunOS, there were two ways to create a process: calling the fork(2) system call or calling the vfork(2) system call. Vfork is similar to fork but was built as an optimization after the observation that, most times, a fork(2) call is immediately followed by an execve(2) call, and so there is no need to do all of the work of a full fork. In particular, one of the semantics is that after calling vfork, the parent process will not be scheduled to run again until after the child either calls execve(2) or exits. Because of this, it was decided that there was no reason to incorporate support for vfork(2) into the code that detected fork bombs. However, it turned out that vfork(2) was exploitable. In particular, a vfork based bomb could simply execute itself if, for instance, its executable was stored in some known location.

The other interesting thing about the fork bomb killer on the Sun centered around its installation and operation. As previously stated, Grex did not have the source code for SunOS, and so did not have the source code for fork(2). However, SunOS had a loadable kernel module interface, and the fork bomb killer was written in terms of this as a loadable device driver. When loaded, it overwrote the address of the real fork in the kernel system call vector, replacing it with a call to itself. It would try to invoke the real fork on the user's behalf, and would detect if the it failed. It then maintained a count of such failures for each user, which was periodically decreased by time-decay code that was latching onto one of the kernel's internal timers. It did not look for total number of fork calls or active processes or anything of that nature, but rather, for fork failures over a given period of time. If, based on the somewhat arbitrary condition of a user having more than fifty fork failures in two seconds, the killer determined that a user was executing a fork bomb, it would walk the process table and send SIGKILL to each process owned by the offender, being sure to propagate the signal to each such process's children, if any, effectively logging the user out. An interesting side effect of the implementation as a loadable kernel module and the implementation of the SunOS LKM interface was that the fork(2). wrapper had a device node associated with it in /dev.

With the move to OpenBSD and new hardware, this was revisited, and a prototype implementation was written but it was deemed not worth the bother: the new system handles a user running a forkbomb without degrading system performance unduly, and the kernel allows you to kill them off. However, the technique remains in the back of our collective minds should this become a problem again in the future.

The Password Database

Originally, Grex used the standard 7th Edition format flat text /etc/passwd file standard under SunOS. However, as the system grew, it became clear that this would not scale, and that using the old crypt(3) based 7th Edition password hash that was also standard under SunOS at that time was less than ideal from a security perspective, as was keeping the hashed passwords in /etc/passwd, where anyone could read them. In a gradual evolution, all three of these problems were addressed and eventually the entire password subsystem was replaced with custom code to both index the password database and provide a shadow password file, unreadable to most users. Also, the Grex staff came up with a new algorithm for hashing the passwords themselves that performed significantly better than and had several security advantages over the standard, DES-based algorithm used in SunOS's crypt(3) routine. It was also thought that passwords hashed with this algorithm might be directly incorporated as keys into, e.g., a modified Kerberos V key distribution center as the authentication basis for a networked Grex spread across several machines. More details, as well as some source code, can be found here.

Unfortunately, the indexing scheme was not compatible with Sun's tools, and the Grex staff had to build and maintain custom, non-standard utilities to administer the password database. Further, the standard tools were not removed from the system but would corrupt the database if used, requiring a laborious rebuild process: this caught more than one new system administrator (and an unsuspecting user community) by surprise. However, OpenBSD shipped with a password database indexing system that performed well enough on modern hardware that this customization was deemed unnecessary and not carried forward. Further, a shadow password database is a standard part of the OpenBSD password subsystem.

Grex's custom password hashing algorithm, however, was another matter. Originally a major improvement over the standard crypt(3), most of Grex's users' passwords had been converted to use it over the years. Since it is practically impossible to invert the hashing process to recover the original password and hash with another algorithm, and since Grex still had some hope for building a KDC based on user's encrypted passwords as keys, and in order to avoid forcing users to change their passwords, the Grex staff implemented support for the Grex hashing algorithm for OpenBSD using the BSD Authentication System.

However, this had several problems of its own. First, the hash itself was based on the HMAC transformation, but all the inputs to it except for the password itself were fixed, eliminating the unique properties of HMACs that make them useful, and effectively rendering the security of the algorithm equivalent to that of the underlying hash function. Further, it had to be maintained: every time the system was upgraded, support for the hashing function would have to be patched into it. This would be doubly true for any sort of custom Kerberos KDC. One of the benefits of moving to OpenBSD was a much reduced maintenance burden: by continuing to use a custom hashing algorithm, we were negating that to some extent. So, in 2007, Grex moved to the blowfish-based hashing algorithm used with OpenBSD's bcrypt(3) hashing implementation.

The method used to migrate is interesting and bears mentioning here: the process was completely transparent to users, and involved two major steps. The first, and most obvious, was to modify the code that creates users on Grex to use bcrypt(3) instead of Grex's custom hash. Next, we unmodified the passwd(1) program so that it would produce standard passwords bcrypt(3) when run. Finally, and most interestingly, we instrumented the various programs that performed password authentication to detect whether a user's password had been hashed using bcrypt(3) or Grex's algorithm. If the latter, it would rehash it using bcrypt(3) and store the result in the password database. In this way, we were able to rapidly convert the entire user population's passwords to use the standard algorithm. Further, if Grex ever revisits the idea of using, e.g., Kerberos, this will likely be the main way that we add users to the KDC.

As of now, Grex's password database and the passwords in it are completely standard.

Queueing Telnet and idled

On Grex's Sun computers, pseudo-tty devices (ptys) for incoming network connections were a scarce resource, as the system was sufficiently underpowered that it could not support that many users at one time and ptys were limited in order to keep the system relatively responsive. An unfortunate consequence was that demand exceeded supply, and it became difficult for many users to get a pty, making Grex difficult to use at best. Some users developed "war-telneter" scripts to telnet to Grex repeatedly until they got a pty, further slowing the system down. This led to two consequences: the development of a queueing telnet daemon and the running of a program that looked for and logged out idle users. The latter was the open source idled program, while the former was developed in house and would place incoming telnet connections on a queue if more than a certain number of users were logged in at once. Eventually, queued users would obtain a pty as other users logged off.

With the move to OpenBSD, statistical analysis was performed on historic queue size data and it was found that, with a total of 128 ptys available for user logins, the queue was almost never used. Further, grex's new machine was sufficiently powerful that it could handle this load easily. Consequently, the queueing telnet daemon was not brought forward to OpenBSD.

With the elimination of the queueing telnet daemon and an abundance of resources, it was soon determined that the idle daemon wasn't doing very much good and it, too, was removed.

Periodically, this causes problems as people launch denial of service attacks against Grex, trying to tie up its ptys and other resources. Unfortunately, the telnet queue could not have helped against this: an attacker would first simply tie up the legitimate ptys, and then just fill the queue. The end result would be the same, in that legitimate users would be denied the ability to use Grex. Given the intractability of combating denial of service attacks in general, it was deemed not worth the effort. However, recent attacks may require Grex's staff to revisit this issue.

$Id: system.xhtml 1547 2016-09-25 14:57:21Z kentn $